<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Phyloseminar</title>
    <link>http://phyloseminar.org/</link>
    <description>phyloseminar -- a free online seminar about phylogenetics</description>
    <item>
      <title>
        Arianna Miles-Jay: Applying phylogenetics in public health: Past, present, and potential for the future, 2025-08-12 09:00 PDT
      </title>
      <link>http://phyloseminar.org/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the rapid growth of pathogen genomics in public health comes the increasing potential for applying phylogenetic methods within the applied public health space. While there is an immense availability of data, the infrastructure, systems, and workforce within public health are largely not designed to maximize that potential. In this seminar, Arianna will discuss some of the ways phylogenetic methods have been applied within public health to date. She will also share some of the unique challenges, opportunities, and hopes for the future for translating findings from phylogenetic approaches to public health action.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>2025-06-15T10:00:00-07:00</pubDate>
      <guid>150milesJay</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>
        Alli Black: Practicing the theory: Applying genomic epidemiology to guide public health action., 2025-07-15 09:00 PDT
      </title>
      <link>http://phyloseminar.org/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this seminar I&#39;ll describe the bread and butter applications of genomic epidemiology in public health practice, contrast genomic epidemiological research projects with the realities of applied genomic epidemiology in practice, and highlight the unique opportunities and particular challenges one encounters in public health. To make this more concrete, I&#39;ll show examples from our recent work using genomics to support H5N1 outbreak response in Washington. I&#39;ll close with some of the opportunities I see for academic research to strengthen applied genomic epidemiology in public health practice.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>2025-06-17T10:00:00-07:00</pubDate>
      <guid>149black</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>
        Henry Kunerth: Genomic Surveillance of Human Respiratory Syncytial Virus in Minnesota – Statewide Efforts, Global Impacts, 2025-06-17 09:00 PDT
      </title>
      <link>http://phyloseminar.org/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the past two respiratory seasons, we’ve successfully sequenced over 3,000 human Respiratory Syncytial Virus (hRSV) genomes at the Minnesota Department of Health – Infectious Disease Laboratory. These efforts began as a foil to our SARS-CoV-2 sequencing efforts, but have grown into a pioneer project for tracking the evolution of this widespread pathogen. In this seminar, Henry will discuss the development of this surveillance program, the application of phylogenetics to identify and track the emergence and seasonal changes in hRSV clades, the applications for genomic epidemiology, and how the efforts of one state lab can have widespread impact on the global picture of the virus. He will also touch on some ongoing work exploring efforts to identify sites that are shaped by positive natural selection and how some may play a role in vaccine and drug resistance. Finally, we’ll wrap up with a discussion about some of the challenges and goals for refining these methods and expanding hRSV surveillance nationally and globally.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>2025-05-29T10:00:00-07:00</pubDate>
      <guid>148kunerth</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>
        Antoine Koehl: Deep Models of Protein Evolution, 2025-05-27 09:00 PDT
      </title>
      <link>http://phyloseminar.org/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Models of protein evolution seek to quantify how proteins evolve over time while experiencing intricate constraints and adapting new functions. These models are the engine of phylogenetics, enabling, amongst other applications, phylogenetic tree reconstruction and ancestral sequence inference. Classic and contemporary work in protein sequence modeling incompletely address each others’ shortcomings - the gold standard classical models (e.g. WAG, LG) are limited by a need to consider sites in protein sequences as evolving independently, and while deep protein language models are able to account for interactions between sites, they lack an explicit time component. Here, we tackle this challenge by introducing a framework for training deep evolutionary models on protein family trees. By constructing comprehensive training datasets, we are able to train a deep generative model that bridges this methodological gap to model evolutionary transitions on unaligned sequence pairs, capturing the full spectrum of evolutionary forces including insertions and deletions. Our model, termed PEINT (Protein Evolution IN Time) significantly outperforms classical evolutionary approaches and enables realistic simulations of evolutionary trajectories. This advance opens new possibilities to understand and harness evolution for protein design, variant effect prediction, viral evolution forecasting, and statistical phylogenetics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>2025-05-20T10:00:00-07:00</pubDate>
      <guid>147koehl</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>
        Pierre Barrat-Charlaix: Reconstruction of ancestral protein sequences using autoregressive generative models, 2025-05-21 09:30 PDT
      </title>
      <link>http://phyloseminar.org/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ancestral sequence reconstruction (ASR) is an important tool to understand how protein structure and function changed over the course of evolution. It essentially relies on models of sequence evolution that can quantitatively describe changes in a sequence over time. Such models usually consider that sequence positions evolve independently from each other and neglect epistasis: the context-dependence of the effect of mutations. On the other hands, the last years have seen major developments in the field of generative protein models, which learn constraints associated with structure and function from large ensembles of evolutionarily related proteins. Here, we show that it is possible to extend a specific type of generative model to describe the evolution of sequences in time while taking epistasis into account. We apply the developed technique to the problem of Ancestral Sequence Reconstruction (ASR): given a protein family and its evolutionary tree, we try to infer the sequences of extinct ancestors.
Using both simulations and data coming from experimental evolution we show that our method outperforms state-of-the-art ones.
Moreover, it allows for sampling a greater diversity of potential ancestors, allowing for a less biased characterization of ancestral sequences.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>2025-04-29T10:00:00-07:00</pubDate>
      <guid>146barratCharlaix</guid>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
