<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Phyloseminar</title>
    <link>http://phyloseminar.org/</link>
    <description>phyloseminar -- a free online seminar about phylogenetics</description>
    <item>
      <title>
        Trevor Graham: Quantitative measurement of cancer evolutionary history from single-sample bulk DNA methylation data, 2025-11-24 09:00 PST
      </title>
      <link>http://phyloseminar.org/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cancers evolve. Current methods to measure evolutionary dynamics rely on genome sequencing of multiple samples from each tumour to detect subclonal mutations and using them to perform phylogenetic tree inference. In this talk I will show a very different approach that uses only single-sample bulk DNA methylation data to provide an unexpectedly rich read out of the clonal history of tumour evolution. Our approach relies on “fluctuating DNA methylation” - the random loss and gain of methylation at particular CpG sites which are evolutionarily neutral. We infer evolutionary history by modelling the site frequency spectrum of fluctuating methylation within single samples. I will show applications in haematological cancers where we use the approach to measure, in 1000s of cancers, tumour age, growth rate and various features of subclonal dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>2025-10-20T10:00:00-07:00</pubDate>
      <guid>153graham</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>
        Ben Raphael: Tumor Evolution over Space and Time, 2025-10-20 09:00 PDT
      </title>
      <link>http://phyloseminar.org/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cancer is the result of an evolutionary process where genomic mutations and epigenetic alterations accumulate in cells that form a tumor.  Modern single-cell and spatial sequencing technologies enable the measurement of mutations at thousands of cells or spatial locations within a tumor.  However, due to technical limitations these measurements are typically sparse with high rates of missing data.  In this talk, I will describe algorithms that overcome these limitations and: (1) Reconstruct tumor evolution in space from large copy number aberrations, revealing directions of tumor growth in 2D and 3D; (2) Analyze tumor evolution over time and in response to treatment using longitudinal single-cell sequencing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>2025-10-20T10:00:00-07:00</pubDate>
      <guid>152raphael</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>
        Niko Beerenwinkel: Modeling tumor progression from single-cell sequencing data, 2025-09-16 09:00 PDT
      </title>
      <link>http://phyloseminar.org/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cancer progression is a somatic evolutionary process characterized by the accumulation of genetic alterations and responsible for tumor growth, clinical progression, and drug resistance development. I will present probabilistic models for reconstructing the evolutionary history of a tumor from single-cell sequencing data, including efficient inference algorithms for mutation calling and for learning tumor phylogenies from mutation and copy number data. I will also discuss computational methods for finding common patterns of tumor evolution among patients and for inferring the underlying cellular fitness landscape of cancer evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>2025-09-08T10:00:00-07:00</pubDate>
      <guid>151beerenwinkel</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>
        Arianna Miles-Jay: Applying phylogenetics in public health: Past, present, and potential for the future, 2025-08-12 09:00 PDT
      </title>
      <link>http://phyloseminar.org/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the rapid growth of pathogen genomics in public health comes the increasing potential for applying phylogenetic methods within the applied public health space. While there is an immense availability of data, the infrastructure, systems, and workforce within public health are largely not designed to maximize that potential. In this seminar, Arianna will discuss some of the ways phylogenetic methods have been applied within public health to date. She will also share some of the unique challenges, opportunities, and hopes for the future for translating findings from phylogenetic approaches to public health action.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>2025-06-15T10:00:00-07:00</pubDate>
      <guid>150milesJay</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>
        Alli Black: Practicing the theory: Applying genomic epidemiology to guide public health action., 2025-07-15 09:00 PDT
      </title>
      <link>http://phyloseminar.org/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this seminar I&#39;ll describe the bread and butter applications of genomic epidemiology in public health practice, contrast genomic epidemiological research projects with the realities of applied genomic epidemiology in practice, and highlight the unique opportunities and particular challenges one encounters in public health. To make this more concrete, I&#39;ll show examples from our recent work using genomics to support H5N1 outbreak response in Washington. I&#39;ll close with some of the opportunities I see for academic research to strengthen applied genomic epidemiology in public health practice.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>2025-06-17T10:00:00-07:00</pubDate>
      <guid>149black</guid>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
