<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Phyloseminar</title>
    <link>http://phyloseminar.org/</link>
    <description>phyloseminar -- a free online seminar about phylogenetics</description>
    <item>
      <title>
        Pierre Barrat-Charlaix: Reconstruction of ancestral protein sequences using autoregressive generative models, 2025-05-20 09:00 PDT
      </title>
      <link>http://phyloseminar.org/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ancestral sequence reconstruction (ASR) is an important tool to understand how protein structure and function changed over the course of evolution. It essentially relies on models of sequence evolution that can quantitatively describe changes in a sequence over time. Such models usually consider that sequence positions evolve independently from each other and neglect epistasis: the context-dependence of the effect of mutations. On the other hands, the last years have seen major developments in the field of generative protein models, which learn constraints associated with structure and function from large ensembles of evolutionarily related proteins. Here, we show that it is possible to extend a specific type of generative model to describe the evolution of sequences in time while taking epistasis into account. We apply the developed technique to the problem of Ancestral Sequence Reconstruction (ASR): given a protein family and its evolutionary tree, we try to infer the sequences of extinct ancestors.
Using both simulations and data coming from experimental evolution we show that our method outperforms state-of-the-art ones.
Moreover, it allows for sampling a greater diversity of potential ancestors, allowing for a less biased characterization of ancestral sequences.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>2025-04-29T10:00:00-07:00</pubDate>
      <guid>146barratCharlaix</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>
        Faruck Morcos: Modeling sequence evolution by learning epistatic terms from protein families, 2025-04-29 09:00 PDT
      </title>
      <link>http://phyloseminar.org/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The use of coevolutionary information, i.e. the knowledge of amino acid or nucleotide interactions maintained through evolution in each protein family, has provided a framework to study structural biology in a predictive manner. Amino acid couplings, obtained from inference algorithms like Direct Coupling Analysis, have been fundamental to predict non-local interactions in protein three-dimensional structure, being now the core of state-of-the-art protein structure prediction algorithms. Coevolutionary information has had an impact in understanding conformational plasticity, complex prediction in molecular interactions and specificity in signal transduction and predicting the effect of mutations. In this seminar I will discuss new directions in the study of global models of sequence evolution, primarily focused on the integration of theory and experiment. I will present recent advances in my lab integrating the statistical mechanics of sequences to develop a model of sequence evolution called Sequence Evolution with Epistatic Contributions (SEEC) that unifies several statistical features of independent models by integrating epistatic contributions and context dependance in the formulation of evolutionary landscapes. We then demonstrate how this model can produce, in silico, evolved sequences that are functional, in vivo, even after a large number of mutational events proposed by the dynamics of the model.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>2025-03-26T10:00:00-07:00</pubDate>
      <guid>145morcos</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>
        Qianying Lin: Segment trees can not identify viral genomic reassortment, 2025-03-12 09:00 PDT
      </title>
      <link>http://phyloseminar.org/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Reassortment is an evolutionary process common in viruses with segmented genomes. These viruses can swap whole genomic segments during cellular co-infection, giving rise to novel progeny, i.e., the reassortant, formed from the mixture of parental segments. The reassortant can lead to severe illness, vaccine-elicited immunity escape, increased fitness, and access to new hosts, which pressures public health surveillance, disease control, and prevention. In light of the Markov Genealogy Process, we can simultaneously model the interdependent viral evolution of each segment tree in the context of a given epidemiological process, incorporated with genealogical changes associated with specified reassortment rates. In doing so, we argue that, in general, the number and pattern of reassortment events are not identifiable from segment trees alone, even with theoretically ideal data. We call this fact the fundamental problem of reassortment, which we illustrate using the concept of the &#34;first-infection tree&#34;, a typically but not always counterfactual genealogy that would have been observed in the segment trees had no reassortment occurred. Further, we illustrate four problems that can arise logically in inferring reassortment events. Using simulated data, we show that these problems are common and can distort our perception of reassortment, even in small data sets. Finally, we discuss how existing methods can be augmented or adapted to account for the fundamental problem of reassortment and the four additional situations that can complicate the inference of reassortment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>2025-02-11T10:00:00-08:00</pubDate>
      <guid>144lin</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>
        Aaron King: Phylodynamics via Markov genealogy processes (2/2), 2025-02-11 09:00 PST
      </title>
      <link>http://phyloseminar.org/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Phylodynamic inference allows us to extract information on determinants of epidemic dynamics from sampled pathogen genomes. Specifically, phylodynamics seeks to infer the structure and parameterization of dynamic population models from patterns of shared ancestry. A key problem in phylodynamics has been a mismatch between inference methodology and epidemiological models: the approximations that must be made to perform inference conflict with questions of great interest. I will describe recent work in which we have obtained exact expressions for phylodynamic likelihoods associated with population models of (almost) arbitrary complexity. These results unify and strictly extend existing approaches and broaden the scope of phylodynamic inference methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the second talk, I will deduce an exact expression for the likelihood of an observed genealogy, as the solution to a well-defined filter equation, which can be solved numerically using standard Monte Carlo techniques. I will conclude by highlighting the need for improved algorithms and indicating some open questions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>2025-01-14T10:00:00-08:00</pubDate>
      <guid>143king</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>
        Aaron King: Phylodynamics via Markov genealogy processes (1/2), 2025-01-14 09:00 PST
      </title>
      <link>http://phyloseminar.org/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Phylodynamic inference allows us to extract information on determinants of epidemic dynamics from sampled pathogen genomes. Specifically, phylodynamics seeks to infer the structure and parameterization of dynamic population models from patterns of shared ancestry. A key problem in phylodynamics has been a mismatch between inference methodology and epidemiological models: the approximations that must be made to perform inference conflict with questions of great interest. I will describe recent work in which we have obtained exact expressions for phylodynamic likelihoods associated with population models of (almost) arbitrary complexity. These results unify and strictly extend existing approaches and broaden the scope of phylodynamic inference methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first talk, I will discuss what phylodynamics is, describe commonly used approaches to phylodynamic inference, and explain the need for better methods. I will then show how so-called Markov genealogy processes provide a useful formalism for the problem. In particular, I will show how every discretely structured Markov population process induces a unique Markov process in the space of genealogies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>2024-12-20T20:00:00-08:00</pubDate>
      <guid>142king</guid>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
